Trees are wonderful arenas for discovery
الأشجار حلبة رائعة للاستكتشاف
because of their tall stature, their complex structure,
بسبب طول قامتها، وبنيتها المعقدة،
the biodiversity they foster and their quiet beauty.
وتعزيزها للتنوع البيولوجي وجمالها الهادئ.
I used to climb trees for fun all the time
اعتدت على تسلق الأشجار من أجل المتعة في كل وقت
and now, as a grown-up, I have made my profession understanding trees
والآن، كانسانه كبيرة وعاقلة، جعلت مهنتي فهم الأشجار
and forests, through the medium of science.
والغابات ، من خلال العلم.
The most mysterious part of forests is the upper tree canopy.
الجزء الأكثر غموضا من الغابات هي مظلة الشجرة العليا.
And Dr. Terry Erwin, in 1983,
والدكتور اروين تيري، في عام ١٩٨٣،
called the canopy, "the last biotic frontier."
دعا هذه المظلة "آخر الحدود الحيوية".
I'd like to take you all on a journey up to the forest canopy,
أود أن أخذكم جميعا في رحلة للوصول إلى مظلة الغابات،
and share with you what canopy researchers are asking
وأطلعكم على ما يبحث عنه الباحثين
and also how they're communicating with other people outside of science.
وأيضا كيف انهم يتواصلون مع الآخرين خارج العلم.
Let's start our journey on the forest floor
لنبدأ رحلتنا في ارض الغابات
of one of my study sites in Costa Rica.
واحد من مواقع دراستي في كوستاريكا.
Because of the overhanging leaves and branches,
بسبب الأوراق والفروع المتدلية،
you'll notice that the understory is very dark,
ستلاحظ أن منطقة الجذوع مظلمة جدا،
it's very still.
انها ثابتة جدا.
And what I'd like to do is take you up to the canopy,
وما أود القيام به هو اخذكم الى القبة،
not by putting all of you into ropes and harnesses,
ليس من خلال وضع كل منكم في حبال وسرج احزمة،
but rather showing you a very short clip
ولكن بعرض مقطع قصير جدا
from a National Geographic film called "Heroes of the High Frontier."
من فيلم ناشيونال جيوغرافيك يسمى "أبطال من الحدود العليا".
This was filmed in Monteverde, Costa Rica
تم تصوير هذا في ماونتفيردي، كوستاريكا
and I think it gives us the best impression of what it's like
واعتقد انه يعطينا انطباعا أفضل من ما يشبه
to climb a giant strangler fig.
لتسلق شجرة التين العملاقة.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
(Growling)
(دمدمة)
(Rustling)
(حفيف)
So what you'll see up there is that it's really like the atmosphere of an open field,
فالذي سوف ترونه فوق هو أنه مثل الجو في حقل مفتوح،
and there are tremendous numbers of plants and animals that have adapted
وهناك أعداد هائلة من النباتات والحيوانات التي تكيفت
to make their way and their life in the canopy.
ليشقوا طريقهم وحياتهم في المظلة.
Common groups, like the sloth here, have clear adaptations
المجموعات المشتركة، مثل الكسلان هنا، لديها تكييف واضح
for forest canopies, hanging on with their very strong claws.
لمظلات الغابة، متعلقين بمخالبهم القوية جدا.
But I'd like to describe to you a more subtle kind of diversity
ولكن أود أن أصف لكم نوع أكثر دهاء من التنوع
and tell you about the ants.
واخبركم عن النمل.
There are 10,000 species of ants that taxonomists --
هناك 10000 نوع من مصنف النمل --
people who describe and name animals -- have named.
وقد سمى -- الناس الذين يصفون اسماء الحيوانات.
4,000 of those ants live exclusively in the forest canopy.
4000 من تلك النمل تعيش على وجه الحصر في ظلة الغابات.
One of the reasons I tell you about ants
أحد الأسباب أنا اقول لكم عن النمل
is because of my husband, who is in fact an ant taxonomist
لأن زوجي، الذي هو في الواقع اختصاصي تصنيف النمل
and when we got married, he promised to name an ant after me, which he did --
وعد عندما تزوجنا، انه سوف يسمي نملة على اسمي ، وهذا ما فعله فعلاً --
Procryptocerus nalini, a canopy ant.
ناليني، نملة لمظلة الشجرة
We've had two children, August Andrew and Erika
لقد كان لدينا طفلان، أوغسط أندرو و اريكا
and actually, he named ants after them.
وفعلا، لقد سمي النمل على اسماءهم
So we may be the only family that has an ant named after each one of us.
ونحن قد نكون الأسرة الوحيد التي لها نملة سميت لكل واحد منا.
But my passion -- in addition to Jack and my children --
ولكن شغفي، بالإضافة إلى جاك وأولادي،
are the plants, the so-called epiphytes,
هوالنباتات، وما تسمى بأبيفيتس،
those plants that grow up on trees.
تلك النباتات التي تنمو على الأشجار،
They don't have roots that go into trunks nor to the forest floor.
ليس لديهم الجذور التي تدخل في الجذوع ولا على أرض الغابة.
But rather, it is their leaves that are adapted
ولكن بدلا من ذلك, انها أوراقها التي يتم تكييفها
to intercept the dissolved nutrients that come to them in the form of mist and fog.
لاعتراض المغذيات المذابة التي تأتي لهم في شكل ضباب.
These plants occur in great diversity,
هذه النباتات لديها تنوع كبير،
over 28,000 species around the world.
أكثر من 28000 نوع مختلف في أنحاء العالم.
They grow in tropical forests like this one
تنمو في الغابات المدارية مثل هذه
and they also grow in temperate rainforests, that we find in Washington state.
وتنمو أيضا في الغابات المطيرة المعتدلة، التي نجدها في ولاية واشنطن.
These epiphytes are mainly dominated by the mosses.
هذه النباتات الهوائية أساسا مهيمن عليها بالطحالب.
One thing I want to point out is that underneath these live epiphytes,
شيء واحد أريد أن أشير إلى أن تحت النباتات الهوائية تعيش،
as they die and decompose, they actually construct an arboreal soil,
وهم يموتون ويتتحللون، فإنها في الواقع تبني التربة الشجرية،
both in the temperate zone and in the tropics.
سواء في المناطق المعتدلة والمناطق الاستوائية.
And these mosses, generated by decomposing,
وهذه الطحالب، التي تم إنشاؤها بواسطة الطحالب المتحللة أساسا
are like peat moss in your garden.
مثل الجفت موس في حديقتك،
They have a tremendous capacity for holding on to nutrients and water.
لديهم قدرة هائلة على الاحتفاظ بالسيطرة على المواد الغذائية والمياه.
One of the surprising things I discovered
واحدة من هذه الأشياء المفاجئة التي اكتشفتها
is that, if you pull back with me on those mats of epiphytes,
هو اذا تراجعتم معي في تلك الحصير من النباتات الهوائية
what you'll find underneath them are connections, networks
ما ستجد تحتها هي الاتصالات والشبكات
of what we call canopy roots.
ما نسميه جذور المظلة.
These are not epiphyte roots:
هذه ليست جذور أبيفيتس
these are roots that emerge from the trunk and branch of the host trees themselves.
هذه هي الجذور التي تخرج من جذع وفرع من فروع الأشجار المضيفة نفسها.
And so those epiphytes are actually paying the landlord a bit of rent
وحتى تلك النباتات الهوائية تدفع للمالك قليلا من الإيجار
in exchange for being supported high above the forest floor.
في مقابل دعمها عاليا فوق أرضية الغابة.
I was interested, and my canopy researcher colleagues have been interested
كنت مهتما، وزملائي الباحثين في المظلة
in the dynamics of the canopy plants that live in the forest.
في دينامكيات نباتات المظلة التي تعيش في الغابات.
We've done stripping experiments
لقد قمنا بتجارب تجريد،
where we've removed mats of epiphytes
حيث أزلنا حصيرة النباتات الهوائية
and looked at the rates of recolonization.
ونظرال إلى معدلات إعادة الاستعمار.
We had predicted that they would grow back very quickly
وكان علينا توقع أنها سوف تنمو مرة أخرى بشكل سريع جدا
and that they would come in encroaching from the side.
والتي من شأنها أنها تأتي في التعدي من الجانب
What we found, however, was that they took an extremely long time --
وكان ما وجدناه مع ذلك ، أنها أخذت وقتا طويلا للغاية،
over 20 years -- to regenerate,
أكثر من 20 عاما، للتجديد،
starting from the bottom and growing up.
لتجديد، بدءا من القاع ، و النمو.
And even now, after 25 years,
وحتى الآن، بعد 25 سنة،
they're not up there, they have not recolonized completely.
لم تكتمل في الاعلى ، لم يعاد الاستعمار تماما.
And I use this little image to say
ويمكنني استخدام هذه الصورة قليلا لأقول
this is what happens to mosses.
وهذا هو ما يحدث للطحالب.
If it's gone, it's gone,
إذا انها ذهبت، انها ذهبت،
and if you're really lucky you might get something growing back from the bottom.
وإذا كنت محظوظا حقا قد تحصل على شيء متزايد من أسفل القاع.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So, recolonization is really very slow.
لذا، إعادة الاستعمار هو حقا بطيئ جدا
These canopy communities are fragile.
هذه المجتمعات هشة.
Well, when we look out, you and I, over that canopy
حسنا ، عندما ننظر بها ، أنت وأنا، على أن المظلة
of the intact primary forest,
من الغابات الأولية السليمة
what we see is this enormous carpet of carbon.
ما نراه هو هذه السجادة الهائلة من الكربون.
One of the challenges that canopy researchers are attacking today
واحدة من التحديات التي الباحثين المظلة يهاجمون اليوم
is trying to understand the amount of carbon that is being sequestered.
هو محاولة لفهم كمية الكربون التي يتم عزلها
We know it's a lot,
ونحن نعلم انه كثير،
but we do not yet know the answers to how much,
لكننا لا نعرف حتى الآن الإجابة على مدى ما
and by what processes, carbon is being taken out of the atmosphere,
عمليات امتصاص الكربون من الغلاف الجوي ،
held in its biomass, and moving on through the ecosystem.
و حفظه في الكتلة الحيوية لها، والانتقال خلال النظام الإيكولوجي.
So I hope I've showed you that canopy-dwellers
لذا أرجو أن أكون قد أوضحت لكم أن المظلة وسكانها
are not just insignificant bits of green up high in the canopy
لا يستهان بها كالقليل من الاخضرار عاليا في ظلة
that Tarzan and Jane were interested in,
التي كان طرزان وجين مهتمين بها
but rather that they foster biodiversity
ولكنها إنما تعزز التنوع البيولوجي
contribute to ecosystem nutrient cycles,
وتساهم في دورة غذاء النظام الإيكولوجي،
and they also help to keep our global climate stable.
وأنها تساعد أيضا في الحفاظ على مناخنا العالمي مستقر.
Up in the canopy, if you were sitting next to me
في المظلة، لو كنت جالسا بجانبي،
and you turned around from those primary forest ecosystems,
وإذا درت حول تلك النظم الايكولوجية للغابات الأولية،
you would also see scenes like this.
فسترى مشهدا من هذا القبيل.
Scenes of forest destruction, forest harvesting
مشاهد من تدمير الغابات، قطع الغابات
and forest fragmentation,
و تمزيق الغابات،
thereby making that intact tapestry of the canopy
مما سيجعل النسيج السليم للمظلة
unable to function in the marvelous ways that it has
غير قادرة على العمل بالطريقة الرائعة التي لديها
when it is not disturbed by humans.
عندما لا تزعج من البشر.
I've also looked out on urban places like this
نظرت انا أيضاً الى مثل هذه الأماكن الحضرية
and thought about people who are disassociated from trees in their lives.
وفكرت في الناس الذين ينفصلون عن هذه الأشجار في حياتهم
People who grew up in a place like this
الناس الذين نشأوا في مكان مثل هذا
did not have the opportunity to climb trees and form a relationship with trees
لم يكن لديهم الفرصة لتسلق الأشجار ليقيموا علاقة مع الأشجار
and forests, as I did when I was a young girl.
والغابات ، كما فعلت عندما كنت فتاة صغيرة.
This troubles me.
هذا يزعجني.
Here in 2009, you know, it's not an easy thing to be a forest ecologist,
هنا في 2009، كما تعلمون ، انه ليس بالأمر السهل أن تكون عالم في بيئة الغابات،
gripping ourselves with these kinds of questions
تجتاحنا هذه الأنواع من الأسئلة
and trying to figure out how we can answer them.
ومحاولة لمعرفة كيف يمكننا أن نجيب عليها.
And especially, you know, as a small brown woman
وخاصة، كما تعلمون، وكامرأة صغيرة سمراء
in a little college, in the upper northwest part of our country,
في كلية صغيرة، في الجزء الشمالي الغربي العالي لبلدنا ،
far away from the areas of power and money,
بعيدا من مناطق السلطة والمال،
I really have to ask myself, "What can I do about this?
أنا حقا يجب أن أسأل نفسي، "ماذا يمكنني أن أفعل حيال ذلك؟
How can I reconnect people with trees?"
كيف يمكنني إعادة اتصال الناس مع الأشجار؟ "
Well, I think that I can do something.
حسنا ، أعتقد أنه يمكنني أن أفعل شيئا.
I know that as a scientist, I have information
وأنا أعلم أنه كعالمة، ولدي معلومات
and as a human being, I can communicate with anybody,
وكإنسانة، قادرة على التواصل مع أي شخص،
inside or outside of academia.
داخل أو خارج الدوائر الأكاديمية.
And so, that's what I've begin doing,
وهكذا، هذا ما فعلته،
and so I'd like to unveil the International Canopy Network here.
وهكذا أريد كشف الستارة عن الشبكة الدولية للمظلة هنا.
We consult to the media about canopy questions;
ونحن على تشاور مع وسائل الإعلام حول استفسارات المظلة،
we have a canopy newsletter;
لدينا رسالة المظلة الإخبارية،
we have an email LISTSERV.
لدينا قائمة تعميم بالبريد الإلكتروني،
And so we're trying to disseminate information about the importance of the canopy,
ولذا فإننا نحاول أن نشر المعلومات عن أهمية المظلة،
the beauty of the canopy,
جمال المظلة،
the necessity of intact canopies,
ضرورة وجود المظلات السليمة،
to people outside of academia.
للناس من خارج الأكاديمية.
We also recognize that a lot of the products that we make --
ونحن ندرك أيضا أن الكثير من المنتجات التي ننتجها،
those videos and so forth --
وهذه التسجيلات وغيرها،
you know, they don't reach everybody,
تعلمون، أنها لا تصل إلى الجميع،
and so we've been fostering projects that reach people outside of academia,
وهكذا عززنا المشاريع التي تصل الى الناس من خارج الوسط الأكاديمي،
and outside of the choir that most ecologists preach to.
وخارج فئة علماء البيئة العاديين.
Treetop Barbie is a great example of that.
الشجرة باربي هو مثال عظيم على ذلك.
What we do, my students in my lab and I,
ما نقوم به ، أنا وطلابي في المختبر،
is we buy Barbies from Goodwill and Value Village,
نشتري دمى باربي من محلات النوايا الحسنة وقرية القيمة،
we dress her in clothes that have been made by seamstresses
نلبسها الملابس التي خيطت من قبل الخياطين
and we send her out with a canopy handbook.
ونرسلها للخارج مع كتيب المظلة.
And my feeling is --
وشعوري هو --
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكرا.
-- that we've taken this pop icon and we have just tweaked her a little bit
-- قمنا باخذ هذا الرمز المشهور وقمنا فقط بتعديلها قليلا
to become an ambassador who can carry the message
لتصبح سفيرة يمكن أن تحمل رسالة
that being a woman scientist studying treetops is actually a really great thing.
كونها عالمة امرأة تدرس رؤوس الأشجار و هو في الواقع شيء عظيم حقا.
We've also made partnerships with artists,
لقد قمنا أيضا بشراكات مع الفنانين،
with people who understand and can communicate the aesthetic beauty
مع الناس الذين يفهمون ويمكنهم الاتصال مع الجانب الجمالي
of trees and forest canopies.
من أشجار الغابات والمظلات.
And I'd like to just tell you one of our projects,
وأود أن أقول لكم واحدة من مشاريعنا،
which is the generation of Canopy Confluences.
وهو جيل من ملتقيات المظلة.
What I do is I bring together scientists and artists of all kinds,
ما أقوم به هو أنني أجمع العلماء والفنانين من جميع التخصصات،
and we spend a week in the forest on these little platforms;
نقضي أسبوع في الغابات على هذه المنصات الصغيرة،
and we look at nature, we look at trees, we look at the canopy,
ونحن ننظر إلى الطبيعة، ننظر إلى الأشجار ، إلى المظلة،
and we communicate, and exchange, and express what we see together.
ونحن على اتصال وتبادل، ونعبر عن ما نراه معا.
The results have been fantastic.
وكانت النتائج رائعة.
I'll just give you a few examples.
أنا سوف أعطيكم أمثلة قليلة.
This is a fantastic installation by Bruce Chao
هذا تقليد رائع بواسطة بروس تشاو
who is chair of the Sculpture and Glass Blowing Department
هو رئيس قسم النحت نفخ الزجاج
at Rhode Island School of Design.
في مدرسة التصميم في رود آيلاند.
He saw nests in the canopy at one of our Canopy Confluences
رأى في أعشاش شجرة المظلة في أحد ملتقياتنا للمظلة
in the Pacific Northwest, and created this beautiful sculpture.
في شمال غرب المحيط الهادئ، وكون هذا النحت الجميل.
We've had dance people up in the canopy.
لقد كان لدينا ناس يرقصون على قمة مظلة الشجرة.
Jodi Lomask, and her wonderful troupe Capacitor,
جودي لوماسك، وفرقتها رائعة،
joined me in the canopy in my rainforest site in Costa Rica.
انضمت الي في موقع مظلة الغابات المطيرة في كوستاريكا.
They made a fabulous dance called "Biome."
قدموا رقصة رائع تسمى "بايومي."
They danced in the forest,
ورقصوا في الغابة،
and we are taking this dance, my scientific outreach communications,
اتخذنا هذه الرقصة، لتوعية علمية للاتصال الخارجي،
and also linking up with environmental groups,
وللربط أيضا مع جماعات البيئية
to go to different cities and to perform
للذهاب الى مدن مختلفة ولأداء
the science, the dance and the environmental outreach
العلم والرقص والتوعية البيئية
that we hope will make a difference.
التي نأمل أن تحدث فرقا.
We brought musicians to the canopy,
أحضرنا موسيقيين لشجرة المظلة،
and they made their music -- and it's fantastic music.
وقدموا موسيقاهم، والموسيقى كانت رائعة.
We had wooden flutists, we had oboists,
كان لدينا مزامير خشبية، وأيضاً أوبستس،
we had opera singers, we had guitar players,
كان لدينا مغنين الأوبرا، وعازفين الغيتار،
and we had rap singers.
وكان لدينا مغنين الراب.
And I brought a little segment to give you
وأحضرت قطعة صغيرة لأعطيكم
of Duke Brady's "Canopy Rap."
من برادي ديوك "راب شجرة المظلة".
(Music) That's Duke!
هذا ديوك!
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
This experience of working with Duke
هذه التجربة العمل مع دوق
also led me to initiate a program called Sound Science.
كما أرشدني لبدء برنامج يسمى صوت العلوم.
I saw the power of Duke's song with urban youth --
رأيت قوة أغنية ديوك مع الشباب في المناطق الحضرية،
an audience, you know, I as a middle-aged professor,
جمهور، كما تعلمون ، أنا كأستاذة في منتصف العمر،
I don't have a hope of getting to --
أنا ليس لدي أمل في الوصول الى
in terms of convincing them of the importance of wildlands.
إقناعهم بأهمية البراري.
So I engaged Caution, this rap singer,
لذا وظفت، مغني الراب هذا،
with a group of young people from inner-city Tacoma.
مع مجموعة من الشباب من المدينة الداخلية تاكوما.
We went out to the forest, I would pick up a branch,
خرجنا إلى الغابة، والتقطت غصنا،
Caution would rap on it,
كاوشن سيغني الراب على ذلك،
and suddenly that branch was really cool.
وفجأة كان الغصن رائع حقا.
And then the students would come into our sound studios,
وعندئذ يأتي الطلاب إلى استديوهاتنا الصوتية،
they would make their own rap songs with their own beats.
و يقومون بإعداد أغانيهم الخاصة في الراب مع الالحان الخاصة بهم.
They ended up making a CD
وانتهى الأمر بشريط أغاني
which they took home to their family and friends,
الذي أخذوه إلى المنزل لأسرهم وأصدقائهم،
thereby expressing their own experiences with nature
معربين بذلك عن تجاربهم الخاصة مع الطبيعة
in their own medium.
في وسطهم الخاص.
The final project I'll talk about is one that's very close to my heart,
سوف أقوم بالحديث عن المشروع النهائي وهذا المشروع قريب جدا على قلبي،
and it involves an economic and social value
و هو ينطوي على قيمة اقتصادية واجتماعية
that is associated with epiphytic plants.
ويرتبط ذلك مع محطات النباتات الهوائية.
In the Pacific Northwest,
في شمال غرب المحيط الهادئ
there's a whole industry of moss-harvesting
هناك صناعة كاملة من لحصاد الطحالب
from old-growth forests.
من الغابات قديمة النمو.
These mosses are taken from the forest;
هذه الطحالب تنزع من الغابة
they're used by the floriculture industry, by florists,
لتستخدم في صناعة الزهور، من قبل باعة الزهور،
to make arrangements and make hanging baskets.
لاتخاذ الترتيبات وصنع السلال المعلقة.
It's a 265 million dollar industry
انها صناعة بقيمة 265،000،000 دولار
and it's increasing rapidly.
وانها تتزايد بسرعة.
If you remember that bald guy,
إذا كنت تتذكر ذلك الرجل الأصلع،
you'll know that what has been stripped off of these trunks
عليك أن تعرف أن ما تم خلع هذه جذوع تم
in the Pacific Northwest old-growth forest
في الغابات القديمة لشمال غرب المحيط الهادئ
is going to take decades and decades to come back.
سوف يستغرق عقودا وعقودا من الزمان للنمو من جديد.
So this whole industry is unsustainable.
ذلك كله هو هذه الصناعة التي لا يمكن تحملها.
What can I, as an ecologist, do about that?
ما الذي يمكنني، كخبير في شؤون البيئة، القيام به حيال ذلك؟
Well, my thought was that I could learn how to grow mosses,
حسنا ، كان رأيي أن أتمكن من معرفة كيفية نمو الطحالب
and that way we wouldn't have to take them out of the wild.
وبهذه الطريقة لن يكون علينا إخراجها من الحياة البرية.
And I thought, if I had some partners that could help me with this,
وفكرت، إذا كان لي بعض الشركاء التي يمكن أن يساعدونني في هذا
that would be great.
سوف يكون ذلك رائعا حقاً.
And so, I thought perhaps incarcerated men and women --
وهكذا، اعتقدت ربما المساجين من الرجال والنساء
who don't have access to nature,
الذين لا يستطيعون الوصول إلى الطبيعة،
who often have a lot of time, they often have space,
الذي غالبا ما يكون لها الكثير من الوقت، فإنهم غالبا لديهم المجال،
and you don't need any sharp tools to work with mosses --
وأنت لا تحتاج إلى أي أدوات حادة للعمل مع الطحالب،
would be great partners.
سنكون شركاء رائعين.
And they have become excellent partners.
وأصبحوا شركاء ممتازين.
The best I can imagine.
أفضل مما يمكنني ان اتصور.
They were very enthusiastic.
وكانوا متحمسين للغاية.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
They were incredibly enthusiastic about the work.
وكانوا متحمسين بشكل لا يصدق عن عملهم،
They learned how to distinguish different species of mosses,
تعلموا كيفية التمييز بين أنواع مختلفة من الطحالب،
which, to tell you the truth,
التي، لأقول لكم الحقيقة،
is a lot more than my undergraduate students at the Evergreen College can do.
هو أكثر بكثير مما يمكن لطلابي في كلية ايفرجرين فعله.
And they embraced the idea that they could help develop a research design
واعتنقوا فكرة أنه يمكن أن تساعد على تطوير تصميم البحوث
in order to grow these mosses.
من أجل نمو هذه الطحالب.
We've been successful as partners
لقد نجحنا كشركاء
in figuring out which species grow the fastest,
في معرفة الأنواع التي تنمو أسرع،
and I've just been overwhelmed with how successful this has been.
ولقد ذهلت من مدى نجاح هذا.
Because the prison wardens were very enthusiastic about this as well,
لأن حراس السجن كانوا متحمسين للغاية حول هذا ايضا
I started a Science and Sustainability Seminar in the prisons.
بدأت ندوة العلوم والاستدامة في السجون
I brought my scientific colleagues and sustainability practitioners into the prison.
احضرت زملائي الباحثين والممارسين في الاستدامة الى السجن،
We gave talks once a month,
ولقد بدأنا بالمحاضرات مرة واحدة في الشهر،
and that actually ended up implementing
والتي انتهت فعليا بتنفيذ
some amazing sustainability projects at the prisons --
بعض مشاريع الاستدامة المذهلة في السجون --
organic gardens, worm culture, recycling,
حدائق عضوية، مزارع الديدان، وإعادة التدوير،
water catchment and beekeeping. (Applause)
مستجمعات المياه وتربية النحل.
Our latest endeavor,
المسعى الأخير لدينا، مع منحة
with a grant
(تصفيق)
from the Department of Corrections at Washington state,
بمنحة من ادارة التصحيحات في ولاية واشنطن،
they've asked us to expand this program to three more prisons.
وقد طلبوا منا لتوسيع هذا البرنامج لثلاثة سجون أخرى.
And our new project is having the inmates and ourselves
والمشروع الجديد هو وجود السجناء وأنفسنا
learn how to raise the Oregon spotted frog
تعلم كيفية تربية ضفدع أوريغون المرقط
which is a highly endangered amphibian in Washington state and Oregon.
وهو من البرمائيات المهددة بالانقراض بشكل كبير في ولاية واشنطن وأوريغون.
So they will raise them -- in captivity, of course --
لذلك سوف تربى في الأسر بطبيعة الحال ،
from eggs to tadpoles and onward to frogs.
من البيض للشراغف وما بعده الى الضفادع.
And they will have the pleasure, many of them,
وستكون من دواعي سرورهم، وكثير منهم،
of seeing those frogs that they've raised from eggs and helped develop,
لرؤية هذه الضفادع أنها قد ربيت من البيض وساعدوا على تطورها،
helped nurture, move out into protected wildlands
مساعدة الطبيعة، والخروج إلى البراري المحمية
to augment the number of endangered species out there in the wild.
لزيادة عدد الأنواع المهددة بالانقراض هناك في البرية.
And so, I think for many reasons --
وهكذا، وأعتقد لأسباب عديدة --
ecological, social, economic and perhaps even spiritual --
الايكولوجية والاجتماعية والاقتصادية وربما الروحية --
this has been a tremendous project
لقد كان هذا المشروع الكبير
and I'm really looking forward to
وأنا أتطلع إلى
not only myself and my students doing it,
ليس فقط لنفسي وطلابي بفعل ذلك،
but also to promote and teach other scientists how to do this.
ولكن أيضا لتعزيز وتعليم العلماء الآخرين كيفية القيام بذلك.
As many of you are aware, the world of academia is a rather inward-looking one.
كما تعلمون، فإن العالم الأكاديمي ينظر إلى الداخل.
I'm trying to help researchers move more outward
أحاول مساعدة الباحثين للتحرك نحو الخارج
to have their own partnerships
ليكون لهم شراكاتهم الخاصة
with people outside of the academic community.
مع أشخاص من خارج المجتمع الأكاديمي،
And so I'm hoping that my husband Jack, the ant taxonomist,
وهكذا أنا على أمل أن جاك زوجي، اختصاصي تصنيف النمل،
can perhaps work with Mattel to make Taxonomist Ken.
ربما يمكن أن يعمل مع شركة ماتيل لعمل دمية لاختصاصي التصنيف كين.
Perhaps Ben Zander and Bill Gates could get together
ربما يمكن أن بن زاندر وبيل غيتس ينسجمان معا.
and make an opera about AIDS.
لتقديم أوبرا حول الإيدز.
Or perhaps Al Gore and Naturally 7 could make a song about climate change
أو ربما آل غور وناشورال 7 تقديم أغنيات عن تغير المناخ
that would really make you clap your hands.
من شأنه أن يجعلك حقا تصفق له بيديك.
So, although it's a little bit of a fantasy, I think it's also a reality.
لذا، على الرغم من أن قليلا من القليل من الخيال، وأعتقد أن لها أيضا حقيقة واقعة.
Given the duress that we're feeling environmentally in these times,
ونظرا لأن الإكراه شعور بيئيا في هذه الأوقات
it is time for scientists to reach outward,
لقد حان الوقت للعلماء للوصول إلى الخارج،
and time for those outside of science to reach towards academia as well.
وحان الوقت لأولئك خارج العلم للوصول نحو الأوساط الأكاديمية أيضا.
I started my career with trying to understand the mysteries of forests
لقد بدأت مسيرتي مع محاولة لفهم أسرار الغابات
with the tools of science.
مع أدوات العلم.
By making these partnerships that I described to you,
من خلال جعل هذه الشراكات التي وصفتها لكم
I have really opened my mind and, I have to say, my heart
حقا لقد فتحت ذهني، وعلي ان اقول, قلبي
to have a greater understanding,
لقدر كبير من التفاهم،
to make other discoveries about nature and myself.
لجعل اكتشافات أخرى حول الطبيعة ونفسي
When I look into my heart, I see trees --
عندما أتطلع إلى قلبي، وأرى الأشجار --
this is actually an image of a real heart --
هذا هو في الواقع صورة لقلب حقيقي --
there are trees in our hearts,
وهناك أشجار في قلوبنا،
there are trees in your hearts.
وهناك أشجار في قلوبكم.
When we come to understand nature,
عندما نأتي إلى فهم الطبيعة،
we are touching the most deep, the most important parts of our self.
نحن لمس أجزاء عميقة ومهمة في ذواتنا .
In these partnerships, I have also learned
في هذه الشراكات، أنا أيضاً تعلمت.
that people tend to compartmentalize themselves
أن الناس يميلون إلى تجزئة أنفسهم
into IT people, and movie star people, and scientists,
الى ناس تكنلوجيا المعلومات ،و نجوم السينما، والعلماء،
but when we share nature,
ولكن عندما نشترك في الطبيعة،
when we share our perspectives about nature,
نحن نشاطر وجهات نظرنا حول الطبيعة،
we find a common denominator.
نجد قاسما مشتركا.
Finally, as a scientist and as a person
وأخيرا، كعالمة وكانسانة
and now, as part of the TED community,
والآن، كجزء من مجتمع تيد،
I feel that I have better tools
أشعر بأن لدي أفضل الأدوات
to go out to trees, to go out to forests, to go out to nature,
للخروج إلى الأشجار، والخروج إلى الغابات ، والخروج إلى الطبيعة،
to make new discoveries about nature --
عمل اكتشافات جديدة حول الطبيعة،
and about humans' place in nature
وحول مكان البشر في الطبيعة
wherever we are and whomever you are.
أينما كنا ومهما كنا.
Thank you very much.
أشكركم جميعاً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)